<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Engineering Fantasy</title><link href="http://nafiulis.me/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://nafiulis.me/feeds/rants.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://nafiulis.me/</id><updated>2014-04-29T14:59:00+06:00</updated><entry><title>Old School</title><link href="http://nafiulis.me/old-school.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2014-04-29T14:59:00+06:00</published><updated>2014-04-29T14:59:00+06:00</updated><author><name>Nafiul Islam</name></author><id>tag:nafiulis.me,2014-04-29:old-school.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've realized something about myself. I'm old school. I still use email as my de facto means of communication and when
people &lt;em&gt;older&lt;/em&gt; than I am talk about using twitter as their main means of communication I feel even older.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just recently, I was requesting an email from an acquaintance, and he pretty much said &amp;quot;The guy uses twitter,
you know that right?&amp;quot;. To me that was the wake-up call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I (try to) write something random on twitter every now and then, but the truth is that 140 characters kinda suck.
Sometimes, I just tell myself to &lt;em&gt;cut the crap&lt;/em&gt;, and just write something and I feel that I end up writing Haiku:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
Python much slow. Need static quickness.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or perhaps, this one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
PyCharm, y u no work?&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Messages have to be this short, because you have things like &lt;code&gt;&amp;#64;someone&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;#procrastinating&lt;/code&gt; that need
to be appended if you want to be one of the &lt;em&gt;kool kids&lt;/em&gt;. :P&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realise that you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; convey what you want in a tweet. But what can I say, I like rambling sometimes (like an old
man). But not using twitter isn't the only thing that makes me old.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't listen to the newest songs, I prefer listening to &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kbJcQYVtZMo"&gt;Beethoven's Ode to Joy&lt;/a&gt; or perhaps some more local to where I live like
&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=QmsLor0WNx4"&gt;Tagore's &amp;quot;Majhe Majhe&amp;quot;&lt;/a&gt;. I have nothing against people listening to
&amp;quot;Bad Romance&amp;quot; or whatever, but I feel that people like me who appreciate more subtle music are slowly diminishing in
their numbers. This makes me sad, somewhat like &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SVyza9jzw18"&gt;Rachmaninoff's Vocalise&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not to say that I like nothing other than the classics; I adore &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dvgZkm1xWPE"&gt;Viva La Vida&lt;/a&gt; by Cold Play. But that's just me; perhaps I'm a little wary of the
more popular crap from singers like Rhianna. I don't know, maybe there's something wrong with me or perhaps (and I
feel that this is far more likely) the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The funny thing is that even my more &lt;em&gt;modern&lt;/em&gt; song choices are too &lt;em&gt;old&lt;/em&gt;. Recently, I was talking to a close friend,
and we were talking about different kinds of music. When I said that I &lt;em&gt;still&lt;/em&gt; listen to &amp;quot;Viva La Vida&amp;quot;,
the guy was like &amp;quot;Man, thats old!&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weird thing is I'm a teenager, and I'm not &lt;em&gt;supposed&lt;/em&gt; to be old. But oh well, screw it. I am who I am,
and it ain't going to change any time soon.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="life"></category><category term="music"></category><category term="twitter"></category></entry></feed>